Register of the Niel R. Allen papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Niel R. Allen papers
1915-1931
59001
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
The materials relate to Niel R. Allen, a Second Lieutenant in the 8th Infantry of the U.S. Army during World War I. Most of the material centers on The Duckboard, a newspaper which Allen helped create, edit, and publish for Camp Pontanezen, France.
Allen, Niel R. 1894-1959.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1959.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1894 May 1 Born in Pullman, Whitman County, Washington
1918 Graduated from Stanford University, Palo Alto, California.
1918-1919 Served as Second Lieutenant in the 8th Infantry for the U.S. Army during World War I
1922 Graduated from Stanford Law School as Doctor of Jurisprudence Began practicing law in Grants Pass, Oregon.
1941-1946 Served as the Oregon Republican state chair
1943-1957 Served on the governing board of the State Department of Geology and Mineral Industry, and was Chairman of the Board for six of those years.
1944 Was alternate delegate to the Republican National Convention from Oregon
1945-1959 Was national chariman and vice chairman of the American Legion's Civil Defense Committee
1956 Served as Presidential Elector for Oregon
1959 April 13 Died in Grants Pass, Oregon.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Niel R. Allen papers consist of materials relating to Niel R. Allen, a Second Lieutenant in the 8th Infantry of the U.S. Army during WWI. Most of the material centers on the inception, management, and production of The Duckboard, a newspaper which Allen helped create, edit, and publish for Camp Pontanezen, France, towards the end of the war. Also included in the collection are camp-related materials like bulletins and pamphlets, and some of Allen's personal papers such as his identification card and officer's record book.
Arrangement Statement
Collection is organized into 6 series: Biographical Material; Correspondence; The Duckboard file; Bulletin; Pamphlets; and Pay Vouchers.
United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; Journalists.; World War, 1914-1918--France.
- Biographical Material, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- The Duckboard file, 1915-1931
  - Account Books, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Contracts, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1931
    - Telegrams, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - To and from Niel Allen, 1919-1931
      - Smedley D. Butler, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 6)
      - Charles Chassé, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 7)
      - J. R. Harvey, 1931 (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - Eli Helmick, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      - Mellets, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 10)
      - Ed Keen, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 11)
      - Unidentified, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 12)
      - Miscellany, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - To and from other individuals, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Layout of first issue, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Print copy of 33rd issue, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Receipts, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Stationery, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Miscellany, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 19)
- Bulletin, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 20)
- Pamphlets, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 21)
- Pay vouchers, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 22)